Thomas Harrop

twharrop@gmail.com · tomharrop.io

I am a geneticist working with large-scale genomic and transcriptomic datasets.

I generate data using 2nd- and 3rd-generation sequencing. I use R and python to tidy, analyse and visualise data and communicate results.

About me

Technical skills

I'm an experienced geneticist and molecular biologist. I work on research I've developed myself, and in collaboration with internal, external and commercial research partners.

I am skilled at the entire wet-lab workflow for producing short and long read sequencing libraries, from nucleic acid extraction to library preparation and running sequencing instruments. I have experience with classical genetic approaches with live organisms, including transformation, crosses, microdissection and bioassays.

My main tools for programming and data analysis are Python and R. I'm also experienced with bash scripting. I visualise and communicate my results with ggplot2, Markdown, Pandoc, TeX and a bit of html & css.

Research

I'm interested in research related to agriculture and development, tools and techniques in bioinformatics and evolutionary and comparative biology.

Experience

Research & University positions

2021-Present Academic Specialist (B), Melbourne Bioinformatics,

University of Melbourne, Australia.

In my current position, I provide training and support to researchers and projects using bioinformatics in Melbourne's biosciences precinct.

- 2020-2021 Research Fellow, Biochemistry Department, University of Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand.
 After promotion to Research Fellow, I began developing an independent genomics and bioinformatics research program.
- 2017-2020 Post-doctoral researcher, Laboratory for Evolution and Development, Biochemistry Department, University of Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand.
 In this postdoc position I worked on a project to develop and apply tools to integrate genomic selection to breeding programmes to improve honeybee performance.
- 2016–2017 Post-doctoral researcher, Laboratory for Evolution and Development, Biochemistry Department, University of Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand.
 I worked on a bioprotection project investigating the resistance of Argentine stem weevil to its biological control agent.
- 2014–2016 Post-doctoral researcher, UMR DIADE, Institut de Recherche pour le Développement (IRD), Montpellier, France. We used RNA sequencing to characterise molecular events that occur during development of inflorescence architecture in rice, which affects crop yield, and applied these results to study the effects of selection on gene expression during the parallel domestications of African and Asian rice.
- 2013–2014 Post-doctoral researcher, Department of Plant Breeding and Genetics, Max Planck Institute for Plant Breeding Research, Cologne, Germany.

 At the Max Planck Institute I worked on a bioinformatic and

At the Max Planck Institute I worked on a bioinformatic and molecular biology project to compare the transcriptional response of different land plants to UV-B exposure, which acts as an environmental signal.

Professional positions

- **2004–2007 Medical scientist**, Network Pathology, the Austin Hospital, Heidelberg, Australia.
- **2001–2004** Laboratory assistant, Network Pathology, the Austin Hospital, Heidelberg, Australia.

Education

2006–2012 Doctor of Philosophy, Department of Genetics, the

University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

Thesis: The functions of cytochrome P450s in Drosophila.

During my Ph.D. I used classical genetics and modern molecular biology, including transgenic manipulation of gene expression and comparative studies of gene function, to investigate the functions of cytochrome P450 genes in the

Drosophila genus.

2002–2005 Bachelor of Science with Honours (first class), the University

of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

Awards 2006-2009, Australian Postgraduate Award

Personal information

Languages English (native)

German (<u>TELC Level</u> B2) French (<u>TELC Level</u> B1)

Nationalities Australian and British

Teaching

2021-present COMP90014, Algorithms for Bioinformatics, Masters

of Bioinformatics, The University of Melbourne. Subject

coordinator and lecturer.

BINF90002, Elements of Bioinformatics & COMP90016,

Computational Genomics. Guest lecturer.

2020 GENE412, Genetics Department, The University of Otago.

2017–2019 GENE312 project supervisor, Genetics Department, The

University of Otago.

2007-2011 3rd Year Genetics, Department of Genetics, The University of

Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

2006-2009 High School Biology, Department of Genetics, The University

of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

2006-2008 High School Biology, Gene Technology Access Centre, The

University High School, Parkville, Australia.

2005–2008 1st **Year Genetics**, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

Students (co-)supervised

Current Three students, **Masters of Science (Bioinformatics)**

University of Melbourne.

Sarah Bachelor of Science with Honours, Genetics, University of

Robinson Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand.

Marissa Bachelor of Science with Honours, Genetics, University of

Le Lec Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand.

Swarit Jaisal Master of Science, Life Science Informatics, Universität Bonn,

Germany.

Axel Verdier Master of Science, Sciences et Technologies de l'Information

et de la Communication pour la Santé, Université de

Montpellier, France.

Service

Community Founder and convenor of the **Bioinformaticians' Shed**, for

group people using bioinformatics around the Parkville precinct,

hosted by Melbourne Bioinformatics.

RNA-seq From reads to differentially expressed genes workshop for

Australian BioCommons, 23-24 February 2021.

Reproducible Reproducible research workflows with containers webinar

research for New Zealand eScience Infrastructure (NeSI), 23 July 2020.

Sequencing Invited instructor for the Long-read, long-reach sequencing

workshop workshop. November 2019, ANU, Canberra, Australia.

MapNet Main organiser for the 2018 MapNet conference. November

2018, Dunedin, New Zealand.

Nanopore Main organiser for Genomics Aotearoa's long-read

workshop sequencing workshop. April 2018, Dunedin, New Zealand.

Carpentries Assisting instructor for Carpentries workshops: Data

Carpentry, 2019; RNA-seq-workshop, 2020.

Publications

See my Google scholar profile for the latest list.

Journal articles

- Harrop, T.W.R.[§], Guhlin, J.[§], McLaughlin, G.M., Permina, E., Stockwell, P., Gilligan, J., Le Lec, M.F., Gruber, M.A.M., Quinn, O., Lovegrove, M., Duncan, E.J., Remnant E.J., Langford, K.L., Kronenberg, Z., Press, M.O., Eacker, S.M., Wilson-Rankin, E.E., Purcell, J., Lester, P.J., Dearden, P.K. (2020). High-quality assemblies for three invasive social wasps from the *Vespula* genus. G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics 10 (10): 3479–3488. doi:10.1534/g3.120.401579.
- Harrop, T.W.R., Le Lec, M.F., Jauregui, R., Taylor, S.E., Inwood, S.N., van Stijn, T., Henry, H., Skelly, J., Ganesh, S., Ashby, R.L., Jacobs, J.M.E., Goldson, S.L., Dearden, P.K. (2020). Genetic Diversity in Invasive Populations of Argentine Stem Weevil Associated with Adaptation to Biocontrol. Insects 11 (7): 441. doi:10.3390/insects11070441.
- **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Mantegazza, O., Luong, A.M., Béthune, K., Lorieux, M., Jouannic, S., and Adam, H. (2019). A set of *AP2*-like genes is associated with inflorescence branching and architecture in domesticated rice. Journal of Experimental Botany 70, 5617–5629. doi:10.1093/jxb/erz340.
- Harrop, T.W.R.§, Denecke, S.§, Yang, Y.T., Chan, J., Daborn, P.J., Perry, T., Batterham, P., (2018). Evidence for activation of nitenpyram by a mitochondrial cytochrome P450 in *Drosophila melanogaster*. Pest Management Science 74, 1616–1622. doi:10.1002/ps.4852.
- Harrop, T.W.R.§, Ud Din, I.§, Gregis, V., Osnato, M., Jouannic, S., Adam, H. and Kater, M. (2016). Gene expression profiling of reproductive meristem types in early rice inflorescences by laser microdissection. The Plant Journal 86, 75–88. doi:10.1111/tpj.13147.
- Harrop, T.W.R.[§], Pearce, S.L.[§], Daborn, P.J. and Batterham, P. (2014). Whole-genome expression analysis in the third instar larval midgut of *Drosophila melanogaster*. G3 (Bethesda) 4, 2197–2205. doi:10.1534/g3.114.013870.
- Harrop, T.W.R., Sztal, T., Lumb, C., Good, R.T., Daborn, P.J., Batterham, P. and Chung, H. (2014). Evolutionary changes in gene expression, coding sequence and copynumber at the *Cyp6g1* locus contribute to resistance to multiple insecticides in Drosophila. Plos One 9, e84879. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0084879.

[§] Equal contribution

Contributions to articles

- McCulloch, G.A., Guhlin, J., Dutoit, L., **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Dearden P.K., and Waters, J.M. (2021). Genomic Signatures of Parallel Alpine Adaptation in Recently Evolved Flightless Insects. Molecular Ecology 30 (24): 6677–86. doi:10.1111/mec.16204.
- Dussex, N. et al. (2021). Population Genomics of the Critically Endangered Kākāpō. Cell Genomics 1 (1): 100002. doi:10.1016/j.xgen.2021.100002.
- McCulloch, G.A., Foster, B.J., Dutoit, L., **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Guhlin, J., Dearden, P.K., Waters, J.M. (2020). Genomics Reveals Widespread Ecological Speciation in Flightless Insects. Systematic Biology syaa094. doi:10.1093/sysbio/syaa094.
- Lamichhane, R., Munro, F., **Harrop, T.W.R.**, de la Harpe, S.M., Dearden, P.K., Vernall, A.J., McCall, J.L., Ussher, J.E. (2020). Human liver-derived MAIT cells differ from blood MAIT cells in their metabolism and response to TCR-independent activation. European Journal of Immunology 51: 879–892. doi:10.1002/eji.202048830.
- Morgan, B.M., Brown, A.N., Deo, N., **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Taiaroa, G., Mace, P.D., Wilbanks, S.M., Merriman, T.R., Williams, M.J.A., McCormick, S.P.A. (2020). Nonsynonymous SNPs in *LPA* homologous to plasminogen deficiency mutants represent novel null apo(a) alleles. Journal of Lipid Research 61(3), 432–44. doi:10.1194/jlr.M094540.
- Lamichhane, R., Schneider, M., de la Harpe, S.M., Harrop, T.W.R., Hannaway, R.F., Dearden, P.K., Kirman, J.R., Tyndall, J.D.A., Vernall, A.J., and Ussher, J.E. (2019). TCR- or Cytokine-Activated CD8+ Mucosal-Associated Invariant T Cells Are Rapid Polyfunctional Effectors That Can Coordinate Immune Responses. Cell Reports 28, 3061-3076.e5. doi:10.1016/j.celrep.2019.08.054.
- Guerrero, F.D., Bendele, K.G., Ghaffarim N., Guhlin, J., Gedye, K.R., Lawrence, K.E., Dearden, Harrop, T.W.R., Heath, A.C.G, Lun, Y., Metz, R.P, Teel, P., Perez de Leon, A., Biggs, P.J., Pomroy, W.E., Johnson, C.D., Blood, P.D., Bellgard, S.E., Tompkins, D.M. (2019). The Pacific Biosciences *de novo* assembled genome dataset from a parthenogenetic New Zealand wild population of the longhorned tick, *Haemaphysalis longicornis* Neumann, 1901. Data in Brief 27, 104602. doi:10.1016/j.dib.2019.104602.
- Ta, K. N., Adam. H., Staedler, Y.M., Schönenberger, J., Harrop. T.W.R., Tregear, J., Do, N.V., Gantet, P., Ghesquière, A., and Jouannic, S. (2017). Differences in meristem size and expression of branching genes are associated with variation in panicle phenotype in wild and domesticated African rice. EvoDevo 8: 2. doi:10.1186/s13227-017-0065-y.
- Daborn, P.J., Lumb, C., **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Blasetti, A., Pasricha, S., Morin, S., Mitchell, S.N., Donnelly, M.J., Müller, P. and Batterham, P. (2012). Using *Drosophila melanogaster*

to validate metabolism-based insecticide resistance from insect pests. Insect Biochemistry and Molecular Biology 42, 918–924. doi:10.1016/j.ibmb.2012.09.003.

Book chapters

Cridge, A., **Harrop**, **T.W.R.**, Lovegrove, M., Remnant, E. & Dearden, P. (2017). *Nutrition and Epigenetic Change in Insects: Evidence and Implications*, in Advances in Insect Physiology (ed. Verlinden, H.) 53, 31–54 (Academic Press). <u>doi:10.1016/bs.aiip.2017.06.001</u>

Selected scientific presentations

- Genetic diversity and biocontrol in Argentine stem weevils. Genomics Aotearoa seminar series, New Zealand, 2021.
- The genomes of three invasive social wasps. **Oral presentation** at the Annual Conference of the Genetics Society of Australasia (GSA), Melbourne, Australia, 2019. **Symposium chair**: Genomics & bioinformatics.
- Comparative genomics of sexual and asexual parasitoid wasps from the Microctonus genus.

 Poster presentation at the 7th meeting of the European Society for Evolutionary

 Developmental Biology, Galway, Ireland, 2018.
- Genomics of a weevil pest and its parasitoid biocontrol agent. **Poster presentation** at the Annual Conference of the Genetics Society of Australasia (GSA) with the New Zealand Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (NZSBMB), Dunedin, New Zealand, 2017.
- De novo sequencing of Argentine stem weevil and its parasitoid wasp biocontrol agent.

 Poster presentation at the 10th Annual Arthropod Genomics Symposium, Notre Dame University, South Bend, U.S.A., 2017.
- Sequencing and community annotation of the Vespula vulgaris genome. **Oral presentation** at the Entomological Society of NZ Conference, Wellington, New Zealand, 2017.
- Genes controlling transition of reproductive meristem identity during inflorescence development. **Oral presentation** at the 14th International Symposium on Rice Functional Genomics, Montpellier, France, 2016.
- Mechanisms underlying the parallel evolution of inflorescence phenotype during independent domestication of African and Asian rice. **Contributed oral presentation** at the 6th meeting of the European Society for Evolutionary Developmental Biology, Uppsala, Sweden, 2016. **Joint symposium chair**: Branching across the tree of life.
- Gene expression during O. sativa panicle development. **Invited seminar** at the Agricultural Genetics Institute, Hanoi, Vietnam, 2015.
- Molecular mechanisms underlying the phenotypic convergence of inflorescence architecture in domesticated rice species. **Poster presentation** at the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution annual meeting, Vienna, Austria, 2015.

Transcriptomic analysis of early developmental stages of the rice panicle. **Poster presentation** at the Workshop in Molecular Mechanisms Controlling Flowering, Aiguablava, Spain, 2015

RNA interference of the Cytochrome P450 redox partners Cpr and dare uncovers novel P450 functions in Drosophila melanogaster. **Poster presentation** at the 50th Annual Drosophila Research Conference, Chicago, USA, 2009.

twharrop@gmail.com · tomharrop.io







Melbourne, AUSTRALIA